Guide to the Brooklyn charitable organizations for children collection 1985.106
Brooklyn Historical Society
Brooklyn charitable organizations for children collection
1890-1948
Brooklyn Historical Society
1985.106
0.5 Linear Feet in one manuscript box.
Publications from various childrens' organizations, adoption agencies, training schools, and clubs for adolescents. Materials in the collection include annual reports, promotional booklets, newsletters, event programs, and brochures.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Source and date of acquisition unknown. Formally accessioned in 1985.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically by organization name.
Historical note
The age of social reform and an immigration boom in the mid 19th century brought the plight of ill, impoverished, and disadvantaged citizens to the forefront of concerns in urban cities. New York City was a national leader in addressing the needs of neglected, orphaned, and deliquent children. The earliest charity organizations for children were established during this period; in Brooklyn, they were the Orphan Asylum Society of the City of Brooklyn, founded in 1833, and the Roman Catholic Orphan Asylum Society of Brooklyn, founded in 1834.
Many orphaned or destitute children were also institutionalized in almshouses and asylums. As sentiments evolved about the institutionalization of children, the Children's Law of 1875, passed by the New York State Legislature, mandated that children aged three to sixteen be removed from poorhouses. The law led to an increase in the number of child welfare societies, already relatively high in New York City, promoting foster care, adoptions, and group homes. These independent organizations were contracted by the cities of Brooklyn and New York to provide child care services--a trend that continued after the consolidation of New York City and into the 20th century.
Sources
McDonald, Mary. "Child welfare." In The Encyclopedia of New York City, ed. Kenneth T. Jackson, 215. New Haven: Yale University Press; New York: New-York Historical Society, 1995.
Scope and Contents
Publications from various childrens' organizations, adoption agencies, training schools, and clubs for adolescents. Materials in the collection include annual reports, promotional booklets, newsletters, event programs, and brochures.
Organizations represented in the collection include Asacog House; Bay Ridge Day Nursery; Big Brother Movement; Brooklyn Home for Children; Brooklyn Howard Colored Orphan Asylum; Brooklyn Industrial School Association and Home for Destitute Children; Brooklyn Juvenile Probation Association and Brooklyn Juvenile Protective Association; Brooklyn Kindergarten Society; Brooklyn Training School and Home for Young Girls; Brooks Vacation School of Brooklyn; East End Kindergarten Union of Brooklyn; Flatbush Boys Club and Friendly House Association; Kallman Home for Children; Navy Yard Boys Club; Norwegian Children's Society; Ottilie Orphan Asylum Society and Ottilie Orphan Home of New York; Rebecca Talbot Perkins Adoption Society; and Ridgewood Day Nursery.
Ottilie Orphan Home annual reports provide a list of residents, as well as children admitted to and dismissed from the home, for the year reported. Big Brother Movement annual reports provide a list of Big Brother volunteers in New York City, but not the names of children aided by the organization.
Orphanages -- New York (State) -- New York; Charity organization; Annual reports; Charities -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Children -- Institutional care; Booklets; Children -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Nursery schools -- New York (State) -- New York; School children -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Programs (documents); Brochures; Publications; Newsletters; Brooklyn Training School and Home for Young Girls; Bay Ridge Day Nursery (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Howard Colored Orphan Asylum Society; Brooklyn Juvenile Probation Association; Big Brother Movement (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Juvenile Protective Association (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Navy Yard Boys Club (New York, N.Y.); Asacog Club (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Norwegian Children's Society (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Kallman Home for Children; Ridgewood Day Nursery (New York, N.Y.); Rebecca Talbot Perkins Adoption Society (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Ottilie Orphan Asylum Society of New York; Ottilie Orphan Home (Jamaica, New York, N.Y.); Friendly House Settlement (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Flatbush Boys Club (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brooks Vacation School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); East End Kindergarten Union (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
- Asacog House, 1908 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Annual report.
- Bay Ridge Day Nursery, 1957 (Box 1)
  Biographical / Historical
  Founded in 1917, the Bay Ridge Nursery was a non-sectarian organization created in response to the childcare needs of Bay Ridge residents due to the upheavals of WWI. It initially opened at 969 1/2 4th Avenue. In 1927, the nursery leased a portion of 5114 4th Avenue, and eventually built a building aty 322 44th Street, which was remodeled in 1944. The adjacent lot was purchased in 1954.
  Pamphlet.
- Big Brother Movement, 1931, 1934 (Box 1)
  Annual reports, 1931 and 1934; thirtieth anniversary booklet, 1934.
- Brooklyn Juvenile Probation Association, 1908-1915, 1921, 1923-1929 (Box 1)
  Annual reports.
- Brooklyn Training School and Home for Young Girls, 1890-1937 (Box 1)
  Kirmess Festival benefit program, 1890; annual reports, 1913-1914, 1919-1921, 1922-1925, 1926-1930, 1937.
- Brooks Vacation School, 1897-1898 (Box 1)
- East End Kindergarten Union, 1895-1896 (Box 1)
- Flatbush Boys' Club, 1915-1916, 1942-1946 (Box 1)
  Annual reports, 1915 and 1942-1946; benefit event program, 1916 (also benefitted Friendly House and Little Italy House).
- Friendly House, 1907-1908 (Box 1)
  Related Materials
  See also the 1916 benefit program in the Flatbush Boys' Club folder.
- Howard Colored Orphan Asylum/Orphange and Industrial School, 1906-1910, 1912-1913 (Box 1)
  Annual reports
- Kallman Home for Children, 1944 (Box 1)
- Navy Yard Boys' Club, 1968 (Box 1)
  Newsletter.
- Norwegian Children's Home, 1949 (Box 1)
- Ottilie Orphan (Asylum) Society, 1933-1948 (Box 1)
  Located in Jamaica, Queens.
  Annual reports, 1933, 1936, 1940-1941, 1948; The Ottilie Friend newsletter, 1944-1946.
- Rebecca Talbot Perkins Adoption Society, 1938-1939 (Box 1)
- Ridgewood Day Nursery, 1906-1907 (Box 1)